A Guide to the Records of the Arlington County Department of Health, 1928-1984
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
Records of the Arlington County Department of Health, 1928-1984
Arlington Public Library, Center for Local History
RG 21
9 boxes.
Arlington Co., Va. Department of Health
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
Transfered to Library from Arlington County Department of Human Services, 1988.
Historical Information
The Arlington County Department of Health began operating in 1919 and is still functioning today as the Arlington County Department of Human Services. In 1919, the Arlington County Department of Health was one of the first full time county departments for health services in the nation. Unique for this type of county service, the Department received most of its funding from private rather than public resources.
The Department of Health was organized to improve the county's state of public health by enforcing laws regulating sanitation and disease. Over the years, the Department evolved into a social agency serving the community and enhancing the quality of life through many local social programs. The same spirit of community service has prevailed throughout the Department's history.
Scope and Content
Record Group 21 houses six linear feet of scattered records generated by the Arlington County Department of Health from 1928 through 1984.
This group of records is only a small portion of the department's records and covers a limited time span. Many of the items, however, are truly noteworthy. Of particular interest is the collection of scrapbooks that were compiled for the Health Contests of the Inter Chamber of Rural Health, 1938 1943. The scrapbooks contain miscellaneous materials which outline the achievements of the Department for each year represented. The materials include photographs, charts, posters, pamphlets, and textual narratives.
The record group also houses additional scrapbooks, photographs, departmental annual and miscellaneous reports, surveys, and countywide reports concerning civil defense and disaster survival. In addition, two comprehensive histories of the department are included in the collection. Subgroup 3, Series 2, holds ephemera such as federal and Virginia state blank birth certificates and other health forms.
Arrangement
RG 21 is arranged into three subgroups according to general types of materials. Subgroup 1, Scrapbooks, is organized chronologically. Because of the deteriorating nature of the original scrapbooks, the scrapbook's contents were removed from the mounting and filed in the order they appeared in the original scrapbook. Subgroup 2 first has department annual reports organized chronologically, and then other department-wide surveys chronologically. Finally, Subgroup 3 is organized into series by type of material: other department documents, ephemera, and photographs.
There are 507 black and white original print photographs in this record group. They can be found within scrapbooks and unmounted in Subgroup 3, Series 3.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
Digitized Photos from RG 21
Index Terms
Subjects:
Arlington Co., Va. Department of Health; Public health administration -- United States.; Public health.; Arlington (Va.); Arlington County (Va.)
Contents List
- Scrapbooks
  - "Inter-Chamber Rural Health Conservation Contest Conducted by the United States Chamber of Commerce; Report of the Committee on Public Health of the Arlington County Chamber of Commerce, Arlington, Virginia: Supporting Evidence," 1938 [48 photographs]
    - Population Data; County Manager System of Government, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Personnel; Community Interest and Education, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Life Statistics, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Communicable Disease Control, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Laboratory Service, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Tuberculosis Control, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Syphilis and Gonorrhea Control, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Health Centers, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Maternal Hygiene; Prenatal Clinic, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Infant Hygiene, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Preschool Hygiene; Orthopedic Clinic, 1938 (Box 1)
    - School Hygiene, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Sewatge Disposal; Water and Milk Supplies, 1938 (Box 1)
    - General Sanitation, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Inspections; Physician Questionnaires; Public Health Nursing Sample Chart, 1938 (Box 1)
    - Special Activities; Unofficial Agencies, 1938 (Box 1)
  - "The Inter-Chamber Rural Health Conservation Contest Conducted by the United States Chamber of Commerce; Report of the Committee on Public Health of the Arlington County Chamber of Commerce, Arlington, Virginia, Supporting Evidence," 1939 [21 photographs]
    - County Manager System of Government; County Board; Personnel and Expenditures; Facilities, 1939 (Box 1)
    - Life Loss Statistics; Disease Control; Laboratory Service, 1939 (Box 1)
    - Venereal Disease Clinics; Mother and Infant Care; Tuberculosis Control, 1939 (Box 1)
    - Maternal and Infant Hygiene; Accident Prevention, 1939 (Box 1)
    - Medical Conferences; Preschool Hygiene, 1939 (Box 2)
    - School Hygiene, 1939 (Box 2)
    - President's Birthday Celebration; Crippled Children's Clinic; Visiting Nurse Brochure; Health Care Statistics, 1939 (Box 2)
    - Organizations Concerned with Health; Plumbing Association and Plumbing Inspection, 1939 (Box 2)
    - Trash Collection; Cleanup Week; Health Meetings, 1939 (Box 2)
    - Negro Health Week; Child Health Day; Milk Ordinance, 1939 (Box 2)
  - "The Inter-Chamber Rural Health Conservation Contest Conducted by the United States Chamber of Commerce; Report of the Committee on Public Health of the Arlington County Chamber of Commerce, Arlington, Virginia, Supporting Evidence," 1940 [56 photographs]
    - Health Department Directors and Staff; Health Committee; Visiting Nurses; Equipment, 1940 (Box 2)
    - Vital Statistics; Communicable Diseases; Venereal Disease, 1940 (Box 2)
    - Tuberculosis Control, 1940 (Box 2)
    - Maternity Services; Infant and Preschool Hygiene, 1940 (Box 2)
    - School Hygiene, 1940 (Box 2)
    - General Sanitation; Food and Milk Control, 1940 (Box 2)
    - Inspection of Weights and Measures; Laboratory Service; Community Interest and Education, 1940 (Box 2)
    - General Publicity; Cleanup Campaign; Negro Health Clinics; Inspections, 1940 (Box 2)
  - "The Inter-Chamber Rural Health Conservation Contest Conducted by the United States Chamber of Commerce; Report of the Committee on Public Health of the Arlington County Chamber of Commerce, Arlington, Virginia, Supporting Evidence," 1941 [52 photographs]
    - Index; Management and Staff, 1941 (Box 2)
    - Statistics and Records; Community Health Education, 1941 (Box 2)
    - Clippings - Health Education, Activities, 1941 (Box 2)
    - Acute Communicable Disease Control, 1941 (Box 2)
    - Maternal Hygiene; Pre-Natal; Public Health Nurses; Well Nursing; Well Baby Conference, 1941 (Box 2)
    - Preschool Hygiene; School Hygiene, 1941 (Box 2)
    - Adult Hygiene; General Sanitation, 1941 (Box 2)
    - Food and Milk Control, 1941 (Box 2)
    - Inspection of Food Establishments, 1941 (Box 2)
    - Inspections at Army Contonment [sic], 1941 (Box 2)
    - Support for Local Health Work; Special Activities; Cleanup Week; National Negro Health Week; First Aid Instruction; Infant Care, 1941 (Box 2)
  - "The Inter-Chamber Rural Health Conservation Contest Conducted by the United States Chamber of Commerce and the American Public Health Association; Report of Activities During 1942 by the Committee on Public Health and Safety of the Arlington County Chamber of Commerce, Arlington, Virginia, Supporting Evidence," 1942 [68 photographs]
    - Index; Basic Data and Community Services, 1942 (Box 3)
    - Testimonials; Communicable Disease Control, 1942 (Box 3)
    - Tuberculosis Control; Syphilis and Gonorrhea Control, 1942 (Box 3)
    - Maternal Health; Infant Health, 1942 (Box 3)
    - Preschool Health; School Health, 1942 (Box 3)
    - General Sanitation, 1942 (Box 3)
    - Food Control, 1942 (Box 3)
    - Milk Control; Garbage Disposal, 1942 (Box 3)
    - Housing; War Department Building, 1942 (Box 3)
    - Weights and Measures; Negro Health Week, 1942 (Box 3)
    - Hospital Plans; General Publicity, 1942 (Box 3)
  - "National Health Honor Roll Conducted by the United States Chamber of Commerce, the American Public Health Association, The Canadian Public Health Association, Submitted by the Arlington County Chamber of Commerce, Virginia, Supporting Evidence," 1943 [73 photographs]
    - Health Committee; Annual Report, 1943 (Box 3)
    - Administrative Officers; Description of Services, 1943 (Box 3)
    - Educational Publicity, 1943 (Box 3)
    - Vital Statistics; Disease Control, 1943 (Box 3)
    - Maternal Health; Infant Health; Preschool Health, 1943 (Box 3)
    - School Health, 1943 (Box 3)
    - Water Supplies and Excreta Disposal, 1943 (Box 3)
    - Food Control, 1943 (Box 3)
    - Milk Control, 1943 (Box 3)
    - Housing; Beauty Parlors and Barber Shops, 1943 (Box 3)
    - Weights and Measures; Home Nursing, 1943 (Box 3)
    - Special Activities; National Negro Health Week; New Hospital, 1943 (Box 3)
    - Civil Defense; Miscellaneous, 1943 (Box 3)
  - "Report of Arlington County, Virginia, Department of Health, American Public Relations Association Silver Anvil Awards, 1958." Two copies [19 photos each]
    - Index; Administration; School Health; Public Health; Nursing; Lab; Venereal Disease - Chronic Disease Control, 1958 (Box 3)
    - Sanitation; Residency Training; University Affiliations; Civil Defense; Tuberculosis; Crippled Children; Speech and Hearing; Anti-Convulsive Program, 1958 (Box 3)
    - Mental Hygiene; Retarded Children; State Department of Health; Children's Bureau; Foreign Officials, 1958 (Box 3)
    - Annual Report; Pilot Plan; Residency Program; Miscellaneous Journals, 1958 (Box 3)
    - Publications: Tuberculosis, Crippled Children, Virginia Health Bulletin, Arlington County Crippled Children's Program, Mental Health, 1958 (Box 4)
    - Photographs, 1958 (Box 4)
    - Letters, 1958 (Box 4)
    - More Letters, Honors and Awards, 1958 (Box 4)
  - "Community Health Survey of Arlington County, Virginia, 1942." Howard University student project. [66 photos]
    - Map; Table of Contents; Preface, 1942 (Box 4)
    - County History; Health Department Facilities; Personnel; Sewage System, 1942 (Box 4)
    - Sanitation; Food and Milk Control, 1942 (Box 4)
    - Food; Vital Statistics; Communicable Diseases; Ordinance for Control, 1942 (Box 4)
    - Communicable Diseases (continued); Morbidity Report; Disease Control; Tuberculosis Control, 1942 (Box 5)
    - Venereal Disease; Immunization; Child Health; School Health; Clinics; Health Record Forms, 1942 (Box 5)
    - Industrial Hygiene; Virginia Workman's Compensation Act, 1942 (Box 5)
    - Washington National Airport, A Prominent Industry, 1942 (Box 5)
    - Public Health Nursing; Maternity Service, 1942 (Box 5)
    - Laboratory Service, 1942 (Box 5)
    - National Negro Health Week; lay organizations; Red Cross; Inter-Chamber Conservation Contest; Social Hygiene Board; Recommendations; Criticisms, 1942 (Box 5)
  - "Report of the Arlington Chest X-Ray Survey,"
    - Report, 1948 (Box 5)
- Department Reports, Surveys, and Histories
  - Department of Health Annual Reports 1940-1948 (in two bound volumes) (Box 5)
  - Department of Health annual reports, 1928, 1946-84
    - Reports, 1928 (Box 5)
    - Reports, 1946, 1951-1953 (Box 5)
    - Reports, 1954-1958 (Box 6)
    - Reports, 1959-1961 (Box 6)
    - Reports, 1965, 1967-1970 (Box 6)
    - Reports, 1972-1976 (Box 6)
    - Reports, 1977-1981 (Box 6)
    - Reports, 1982-1984 (Box 6)
    - Commission on Human Resources Annual Reports, 1969, 1957-1959 (Box 6)
  - Other Reports, Surveys and Histories
    - Health Department Outline of Activities and Programs, 1955, 1957-1959 (Box 6)
    - Health Department Outline of Policies and Procedures, 1953 (Box 6)
    - County Health Law Reports, 1952 (Box 7)
    - "Surveys of Local Unofficial Health Agencies", 1953-1958 (Box 7)
    - "Outlines of Residency Training in Public Health in Arlington County," 1958, 1961 (Box 7)
    - Histories of the Arlington County Health Department, 1919-1959 (Box 7)
    - Grant Proposals, Chronic Disease Center, 1963 (1) (Box 7)
    - Grant Proposals, Chronic Disease Center, 1963 (2) (Box 7)
    - Grant Proposals, Referral Center, 1963 (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous County Publications and Photographs
  - 1980 Community Profile
    - Location, 1980 (Box 7)
    - Population, 1980 (Box 7)
    - Social System, 1980 (Box 7)
    - Social System: Policy Information Handbook, 1980 (Box 7)
    - Social System: Wakefield High School Program of Studies, 1981-1982 (Box 7)
    - Social System: School Profiles, 1980 (Box 7)
    - Social System: Agenicies, Statistics, 1980 (Box 7)
  - Other Publications and Ephemera
    - Civil Defense Packet, 19859 (Box 7)
    - Survival Plan (Box 8)
    - Arlington County Health Department Ephemera, 1939, 1942, 1964 (Box 8)
    - Arlington Community Hospital Ephemera, 1950 (Box 8)
  - Photographs
    - Miscellaneous Health Department Images, 1940-1973 (Box 8)
    - Children's Christmas Parties, 1957-1958 (Box 8)
    - Orthopedic Clinic, 1973 (Box 8)
- Oversize
  - Large items from the scrapbooks (Box 9)